Now you know how to execute a block of code if a condition is true.
现在你知道如何在条件为 true 时执行一段代码
But what if you have a different block of code that you
但是如果条件为 false 时
want to execute when that condition is false?
你想执行一段不同的代码呢？
You can use the 'else' keyword to do so.
你可以使用关键字 else
Consider this code, which prints a message indicating
看看这段代码
whether an integer N is even or odd.
它会输出一条消息 表示整数 n 是偶数还是奇数
If N is even,
如果 n 是偶数
this line is run.
运行这行代码
Otherwise, this line is run.
否则运行这行代码
Code indented under the 'else' is what happens when this condition evaluates to false.
当这个条件为 false 时 执行 else 下缩进的代码
The 'else' keyword is always followed by a colon and doesn't need a Boolean expression.
关键字 else 后面始终有一个冒号 不需要布尔表达式
So, if we set N to be 4 like this,
如果我们像这样将 n 设为 4
the if statement here would evaluate to true and we would print the following string.
这个 if 语句将为 true 我们会输出以下字符串
Alternatively, if we set N to be 15,
如果将 n 设为 15
this condition would evaluate to false so we would skip
这个条件将为 false
this block and execute the code under the else.
因此我们将跳过这段代码并执行 else 下面的代码
If you have more than two possible cases,
如果你有两个以上的可能情况
you can also use elif,
还可以使用 elif
short for 'else if',
来处理这种情况
to deal with the situation.
elif 是 else if 的简称
This saves the multiple indentation that would be needed if
这样就避免使用 else 然后在其中使用另一个 if 语句
we used 'else' and then another 'if' statement inside the 'else' block.
出现多个缩进代码段
Like 'if', an elif statement always requires a conditional expression.
和 if 一样 elif 语句始终需要条件表达式
For example, let's say we wanted to print what
例如 假设我们想要输出根据当前季节
to do with the garden based on the current season.
如何处理花园的消息
If we set season equal to spring, like this,
如果将 season 设为 spring 像这样
then we can see that plant the garden is
则可以看到系统输出了第一条消息
printed as its first condition evaluates to true.
因为第一个条件为 true
Alternatively, if we set season to winter,
此外 如果将 season 设为 winter
then each of these conditions will evaluate to false until we had
那么这几个条件都为 false
this condition which will evaluate as true and print stay indoors.
直到这个条件为 true 并输出“stay indoors”
Notice here we're using double equal sign again.
注意 这里我们再次使用了两个等号
Remember, a single equal sign is for assignment like we did
注意 单个等号具有赋值作用
here when we were setting a season as a particular string.
就像此处 我们将 season 设为特定的字符串
Two equal sign is for evaluation where we are evaluating a condition as true or false.
两个等号具有评估作用 我们会评估条件为 true 还是 false